[SPEAKER_01]: So, this is from the Anguttara Nikaya, Book of the Threes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there are these three kinds of purity.
[SPEAKER_01]: What three?
[SPEAKER_01]: Purity of body, speech, and mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what is purity of body?
[SPEAKER_01]: It is when a bhikkhu abstains from killing living creatures, stealing, and in celibacy.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is called purity of body.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what is purity of speech?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's when a bhikkhu abstains from false, malicious, harsh, and
[SPEAKER_01]: This is called purity of speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what is purity of mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's when a bhikkhu, when there is sensual desire internally, understands there is sensual desire internally for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: When there is no sensual desire internally, he understands there is no sensual desire internally for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: He understands how un-arisen sensual desire arises, how arisen sensual desire is abandoned, and how abandoned sensual desire doesn't arise again in the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then it goes on for the other hindrances in the same way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Perversion, second hindrances, second hindrance, indolence and lethargy, then restlessness and anxiety, and also doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then there's also verse,
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, one thing that stands out to me here is concerning the purity of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's take this first hymn for example.
[SPEAKER_01]: It says, what is purity of mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: When there is desire, sensual desire internally, he understands there is sensual desire internally for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, when there's no sensual desire internally, you understand?
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no sensual desire internally for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: And both are defined here as purity.
[SPEAKER_01]: How is that possible?
[SPEAKER_01]: How can there be purity when somebody understands that there's still sensual desire internally?
[SPEAKER_01]: What would you say?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so... That's what I think we sort of...
[SPEAKER_00]: I touched on that in some of the previous talks about patient endurance and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: The recognition that underlies that principle is that, fundamentally, impurity or defilement arises on account of your choices.
[SPEAKER_00]: It never arises by accident.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the five hindrances are, technically, something that isn't
[SPEAKER_00]: Up to you, whether they're there or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you, for example, if you haven't been in seclusion, even for an anahant, those things would still be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why some of the suttas, for example, would say... well, that's... it's not obviously the same thing, because when craving is not there, you cannot say it's the same thing anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the, let's say, the shape... the shape
[SPEAKER_00]: The shell of those things would be essentially the same thing, kind of like dried up, but it's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes the suttas would say like a tree with the root cut off, but like the tree is still there, standing, but dead.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the point is that even for them, like another sutta would, for example, say the Narahant is not
[SPEAKER_00]: Detached externally from things like fame, gain, popularity, and sort of worldly engagements that are not against the precepts, but, you know, happen as a result of circumstance or whatever, they will lose their pleasant abiding here and now.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even in some cases, which is a another way of saying they will lose their abiding free from these five things.
[SPEAKER_00]: In many cases, stories in the suttas, the Buddha would, like, refuse to be visited by people who wanted to just bring offerings to, kind of, just without really any interest in the dhamma, because he knew that that would result in unnecessary engagements that would basically make his mind
[SPEAKER_00]: It's more liable to those things and it's not that, you know, it might sound then as if, oh, he was craving to maintain his samādhi or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it says there, whoever cannot get at ease, at will, that pleasure of renunciation, they would agree to these things, but I won't.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that sounds like, oh, he's attached to his samādhi or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the point is, like, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: In itself, the principle of preferring pleasure and avoiding pain is something that's embedded into the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not, in and of itself, craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Craving is another layer that's added to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's put it that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the point here, then, is that, yes, inevitably, even, like, no matter how diligent you are, how
[SPEAKER_00]: perfectly committed to the to the path you are, there will be times when those things will be there in your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if it were a matter of not having those things in order to be pure, it would mean that basically you could lose your arahantship.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what I just mentioned that says an arahant will lose their pleasant abidings.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says also the unshakable liberation of mind
[SPEAKER_00]: That cannot be lost.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why it's called unshakable.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what this is describing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Meaning, the understanding of your mind, even when it is in such a state, means that you will be unable to make choices on account of sensual desire, on account of ill will.
[SPEAKER_00]: And because of that, I mean, technically, you use, again,
[SPEAKER_00]: In an ordinary person, those states are made what they are, because they act out of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why then, when the acting out has been completely destroyed, you can't call them hindrances anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, in and of itself, like, it's kind of the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's why it requires nuance and caveats need to be made, because otherwise people think also you're saying an arahant still has unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the thing is now, the state, like the whole point,
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, this is exactly what a sotāpanna understands, and that's why they're able to cultivate the path.
[SPEAKER_00]: As a sotāpanna says, he understands that the defilements are gratuitous, like they're kind of... he says they flow in on the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, it means states and your actions on account of it, and your intentions on account of it, are two separate things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is the same thing as saying
[SPEAKER_00]: Unpleasant feeling is one thing, and craving is another thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it sounds kind of... Oh, yeah, of course, that makes sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: But seeing that concretely, means seeing the Four Noble Truths.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's the same with this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, seeing how you can have these mental states, without there being any craving, if you understand that, that would already be stream entry.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why, in the Satipaṭṭhāna Sutta as well, it says, in the mind contemplation section, it says,
[SPEAKER_00]: How does a bhikkhu abide, maintain the perspective of the mind, simultaneously with the mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't say, when he has a passionate mind, he gets rid of it, or he stops thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says, he knows a passionate mind as a passionate mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: He knows an averse mind as an averse mind, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: It lists all these possibilities and permutations.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the end, it says, one who abides like this,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, of course, if you continue abiding in that way, with this recognition of passionate mind as passionate mind and so on, you're essentially... that's what's taking your mind away from that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's, in and of itself, it's not that it's unwholesome for those states to be there, if there's no ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, as it is to say, an arahant is
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, they don't even need to practice samādhi anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yes, if... and that's what a trainee has to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: They have to maintain perspective of these states and genuinely try to free their mind from these states, so that they can
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so that is part of the understanding of how an arisen sensual desire arises and how an arisen sensual desire is abandoned.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the difference there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, and obviously, then, the thing to clarify is, like, you will never be able to
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't have that knowledge and that type of purity, if you haven't beforehand cultivated the freedom from, like completely, freedom from sensual desire, freedom from aversion, freedom from these things, which is always temporary...
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is Sattva Samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you haven't practiced that, like, practicing that is what enables you to, like, when you come back to the normal, sort of, like, dealing with stuff and movement of the mind and so on,
[SPEAKER_00]: All of the wrong assumptions and ignorance and craving can't be there, even though you went back to to baseline, quote-unquote.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, there is some ambiguity here about the words mental.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it talks about sensuality and the other hindrances internally, but then you start it out by saying, no, no, hindrances is when we act out.
[SPEAKER_01]: But we should clear up that acting out is by body, by speech, and by mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is also a mental acting out, which is on the level of
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so, eh... that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's mano, so, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Mano is basically your... you could say it's your... that's where your intention is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why there's that first verse from the Dhammapada that says,
[SPEAKER_00]: It says that's the source of all suffering, like the wheel of the cart follows the ox.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's mano, because that's what your responsibility is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But citta, like, that's, let's say, you know, you have your external environment, like, you know, what's happening around you in the world, and then you have your internal environment, which is your citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: And your actions by mano will influence that internal environment as well, your citta, just like it can influence your external environment.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, like I said, to some extent, that internal environment is not completely in your control.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like it's... sometimes you will have to... the most, sort of, direct obstacle to samādhi is lack of seclusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even if everything else is perfectly
[SPEAKER_00]: In your control, at some point, you will have to abandon seclusion, and that means you will lose your samādhi, because, as it is said, the first jhāna is a cessation of speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as soon as you start speaking, you're back to...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: ...back to the normal kind of state, and that's why restraining speech is so important as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, because it's always connected with your intention, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Like I said before, it is always in your control.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the problem is, there's this natural assumption, again, because of not being able to clearly see that difference between citta and mano, which is...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, if you can see that, that's already... essentially, that is the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you can see that... because, by the way, that's how you see wholesome and unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you know, most of people would just assume, if I have
[SPEAKER_00]: The inclination towards, you know, central thoughts or averse thoughts in my mind, that in itself means I have craving, or I am doing something unwholesome, and therefore I have to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But no, it's... the inclination is there, but you always have like a second step there, that you yourself make in relation to that inclination.
[SPEAKER_00]: And see, it's the same principle
[SPEAKER_00]: As with bodily and verbal action, you don't cut your hands off so that you can't steal anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: A bhikkhu doesn't castrate himself so that he doesn't engage in celibacy.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't, you know, cut your tongue off so that you can't lie and, you know, have harsh speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: You simply don't do it, even though the possibilities
[SPEAKER_00]: And, it's exactly the same principle on a mental level, just that, obviously, it's much more subtle.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have the possibility to engage in the sensual desire, because your mind is in a state of sensual desire, that internal environment is there, but you choosing to then, eh... attend to sensual objects through that sensual desire, that's, that's, eh... that's your own choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is where it all starts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and if you're in seclusion and everything, well, you wouldn't even be able to tell what action by Mano is if you haven't developed the graduate training in seclusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would just be all a jumble, and you would think you're purifying Mano, when in reality you're just trying to get rid of your citta, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, when you have that recognition, then maintaining that purity of Mano will, in return,
[SPEAKER_00]: Calm down the citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's always temporary.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now, somebody finds...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, suppose somebody has some understanding of this distinction.
[SPEAKER_01]: They see citta is affected by sensuality, but now, simultaneously, there's also a sensual thought present, which is on the mano level.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then what?
[SPEAKER_00]: If there is... well, actually, that's a good point.
[SPEAKER_00]: The suttas always talk about abandoning unwholesome thoughts, vitakka, and there's a whole... there's these two famous suttas in the Majjhima Nikāya, Majjhima Nikāya 19, Majjhima Nikāya 20, where it talks about, oh, the monk is practicing diligently and then sensual thoughts, averse thoughts arise, and then he gets rid of them, obliterates them, destroys them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And see, because people don't see that distinction between mano and citta,
[SPEAKER_00]: What they're really doing, they're not just stopping at the threshold of their intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're going further, and they're trying to destroy the entire citta as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't see... Like, again, to give the example of body and speech, they're not just choosing not to take the object, they're cutting their hands off.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, obviously, they don't recognize that because it's a very subtle kind of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Distinction.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, only when you're able to see that division, completely kind of a irreconcilable division, the division between mano and citta, between your intention and that internal environment that pressures you to intend, only when you can see that division, you're able to actually purify your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why, like... Yeah, but to purify mind, which is to purify citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, well, both.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you you're able to... Because, see, if you don't see,
[SPEAKER_00]: This distinction, that's why the suttas say you cannot purify your mind accidentally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like suddenly something happened and my mind is pure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether it's mano or citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, I just had this experience and now it's pure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, see, if you don't see that distinction, on some level, you'll be interfering with citta and trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that in itself is through mano and unwholesome action.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not even... Sure, you can say it's acting out, but it's not on the same level as just body and speech, where like any random person, can you just tell him, hey, stop doing that, and he can.
[SPEAKER_00]: Here, it's like, if you don't see the division, or that sort of line, where your action begins, and the mental state is there on its own,
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything you do is acting out of the mental state.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so... That's why, like, with ignorance, there is activities, simultaneously, that, like, there is action.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, like the whole beginning, like, the fundamental, like, the dependent origination, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: But it is attached to where it starts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, again, citta is, let's say, there's a... one notices aversion on that background mind level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, if one says, that shouldn't be there, and I'm going to do something in order to get rid of that aversion on that citta level, that acting out would be the hindrance of aversion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ironically, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, actually, I don't know if I finished what I was saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: When I mentioned these suttas before, about obliterating thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that is valid.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's true.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's generally saying you have to obliterate these thoughts, but that's referring to your intentions in regard to these mental states.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, like, you know, somebody's... there's a current
[SPEAKER_00]: Going in a certain direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now, you swim with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what you abandon.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you don't, like, the current is not in your control to begin with.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, indirectly now, of course, like, that's what the suttas are saying, actually.
[SPEAKER_00]: When the monk has been purifying his thoughts in this way for a while, then the mind, it says, internally as well, the mind settles down.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, there is not even now the inclination.
[SPEAKER_00]: To make those choices.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, the citta itself has calmed down.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what eventually... You want that to happen in order to cultivate samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you know, but again, if you don't see the distinction between the two, you'll be, oh, yeah, I'm going to obliterate my thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm going to get rid of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what you're really doing is you're fighting with your mental state.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where it becomes like, as we say, management.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your internal environment, in your mind, in the same way you're trying to manage things out there in the world, and that implicitly carries a notion that that internal environment is yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's that, like, even if you're contemplating, oh, this is not mine, this is not mine, to get rid of those thoughts, you're implying that it's yours, because otherwise, like, how, why would you be trying to exert control over something if you know that it's not yours?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, citta can be purified, but that only happens indirectly as a result of having the mental purity on the mana level.
[SPEAKER_01]: To sustain it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now you brought up Majjhima Nikaya in 1920, because those discourses talk about
[SPEAKER_01]: Ways to correctly deal with thoughts, which is on the level of māna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, on the... you could say on the external level, not external when you say... it doesn't mean, like, related to the world or other people.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means, like, that level where your intention is involved, in this context.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whereas, internally, is a level that's kind of not really in your control, but it is fed.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why this is to say, you starve the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can never completely... you can never directly get rid of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can,
[SPEAKER_00]: Abandon them.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can abandon them completely, and that's what the jhānas are.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's never by you getting rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's by ceasing to provide the fuel, which is through the mano level, your intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like a vicious circle.
[SPEAKER_00]: The pressure to act is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You act out.
[SPEAKER_00]: That increases the pressure to act, which makes you act more.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, it becomes like...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the environment that you put, you kind of adding stuff to that internal environment, which is then
[SPEAKER_00]: Making you want to act more and more.
[SPEAKER_00]: The opposite is true now.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eh... it's not that you're fully helpless against it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you learn how to stop acting out through what it... to do what it's pressuring you to do,
[SPEAKER_00]: It starts to come down as well, and then there will be not even an inclination to do that, and that's when the minus actually comes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, again, in terms of understanding the right way of not acting out, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no acting out on the level of citta, which is what we've called internal.
[SPEAKER_01]: That we've now clarified.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then there is the... No, like, the internal level is not where the acting out happens.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, that's...
[SPEAKER_00]: The external...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, this doesn't explicitly call it that way, but you can say external.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's this thing here, and then...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm gonna go here and then you run with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's kind of like a direction from internal to external.
[SPEAKER_00]: You kind of express it in some way, let's say.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even not in the world, but through your even, like, your internal thinking, you express the pressure in the same way, like, when you're pressured to, as it says, to steal or to do something, kind of like, you go and do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, internal, the internal dimension is the one that's not really up to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, mind is not... That is you, in that context.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, then it is up to you to not act out of unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now, suppose that on that level where you are, which is the mono-mind level, there is, let's say, a thought of aversion, or a thought of cruelty.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, are you saying... Then, the practice is also to recognize that, and to endure those
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so, the thing there is, if you start calling it thoughts,
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, that's the way we use the word in English.
[SPEAKER_00]: It kind of refers to both active and passive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whereas in the suttas, vittata always refers to active.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's something you're doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And dhamma, like phenomenon, is something that arises on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in this case, you could say you have dhammas, like mental images, you could say, or a kind of subtle sort of
[SPEAKER_00]: Waves or energies, if you want to call it that, of aversion.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if there is a thought of aversion, a vitaka of aversion, that already involves intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that, you don't have to endure that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, so that shouldn't be there to begin with.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, you have the pressure, but you're not acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what it means to get rid of your vitakas.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then,
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's why that's at the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: You obliterate the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, as soon as they arise, you shouldn't tolerate even for a second.
[SPEAKER_00]: Initially, obviously, you will be trying to do that and you'll be mistake... mistaking the vittakas for the state of mind and you'll be kind of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Trying to get rid of one while you're proliferating the other, and everything will be a muddle.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you have been developing the prerequisites of the grander training, you will get to see that... Because, like, if you can't even restrain your more coarse choices by body and speech, there's just no chance that you'll be able to see this thing that's like, you know, if these are four by four centimeters,
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, one nanometer of diameter.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you just won't be able to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the thing is, yeah, but if you keep at it, eventually, like, again, not kind of continuously questioning yourself, not assuming like, oh, I'm already doing it properly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Eventually, you get to see, oh, so, actually, it's
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't need to constantly be straining myself to not act out by mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't need to be straining myself not to steal something.
[SPEAKER_00]: I just need to do nothing, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, that's what it becomes.
[SPEAKER_00]: You realize, actually, the whole kind of agitation that you had to do something, to get rid of these thoughts, the management, to think the opposite, to do this, all of that was rooted in
[SPEAKER_00]: The same pressure, in the end.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, eh... like I said, it won't be perfect, but eventually you get to see, oh, even that, actually, is an action by Mano.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's then when you, eh... when you're able to, as it says there, like you fully understand how the arisen hindrance came to be
[SPEAKER_00]: How the un-arisen hindrance doesn't arise in the future, how to abandon the arisen hindrance, means that you will not be conflating anymore what's actually your responsibility with that which has arisen on its own, which means all that sort of confusion and agitation and vexation and what do I do, none of that will be there, which means even when you have no samādhi,
[SPEAKER_00]: You perfectly know how to get it back, and nobody can stop you, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, you wouldn't be suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, you know, how the suttas say, it's like, kind of, the hindrances are imprisoners of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, imagine, yeah, you're still in the prison, and you're still in the prison cell, but you have the key for the door.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, yes, you technically you're in the prison, but not really.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's how it is when, like, that's what that purity
[SPEAKER_00]: Have you cleared up this distinction between māna and citta, supposedly, you think?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the other thing I would say, it's a matter as well of repetition.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you know, you have the intellectual kind of reasoning and reading the suttas and so on, and you hear that, yes, there is a difference between these two things.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you have to keep in mind, like,
[SPEAKER_00]: For as long as I'm still... for as long as there's any degree of uncertainty and doubt, that's why authenticity is so important.
[SPEAKER_00]: For as long as there is any liability to... for as long as you feel, again, you're enslaved, you're imprisoned in that, and you're not entirely sure whether you're going to be able to get out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that means, even though, yes, the idea makes sense, you haven't actually understood it, concretely, to the point where, like, those hindrances would cease to be hindrances, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why, like, you know, with the whole contemporary meditation approaches and so on, people feel like, yeah, you know, they're freeing themselves from these hindrances, but, at the end of the day, because there's that lack of authenticity to recognize
[SPEAKER_00]: Actually, I'm still liable to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you know, the only reason why I'm able to...
[SPEAKER_00]: Seemingly get out of the prison cell is because, like, you know, the circumstances are are suitable for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's somebody outside who's helping me get out.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I don't actually have the key where I could get out at will.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when people would realize, you know, if their precious daily setup of meditation two hours a day and a bunch of other external factors were to
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's crucial to keep in mind that freedom from doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's really the criteria.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, because that is one of the hindrances as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the criteria to be able to see whether you actually understood it or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can have as many experiences as you want, where it seems like everything is calm and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, as it says, it's when you understand how these things come to be, how they don't come to be,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when you actually purify yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't say, like, what is mental purity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Here, a bhikkhu doesn't have sensual desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that can happen, like, actually, there's another sutta where, I think we've mentioned that one before, where it says, the five lower fetters, I think that's Majjhima 64, and then this monk just lists them out, kind of in a superficial sense, and the Buddha says, well, if those were the five lower fetters, then a baby would be free from them, because the baby doesn't know what sensual
[SPEAKER_01]: There's that simile in the Manpitmanāṅgapaṭṭhā.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: He doesn't know what sensual desires are.
[SPEAKER_00]: He doesn't know what...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, just not having these things, that doesn't mean anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, because that's the underlying tendencies.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, when we speak about liability, that's the level we're talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, these underlying tendencies are still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And basically, you could frame those underlying tendencies as, okay, right now...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what's the difference between then not having the underlying tendency and
[SPEAKER_00]: Having it, it's like... well, what would happen if my state of mind were to deteriorate?
[SPEAKER_00]: What if I were to lose a pleasant body?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, many people operate with the assumption that that should never happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: But this is not... that's not what this is to say.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eh... if, you know, your mind, that internal environment,
[SPEAKER_00]: Even in your external environment, you're able to cope with difficulties and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if in your internal environment, your own mind that's not yours, your five aggregates, they get out of whack, would you now suffer?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there's millions of things that can, even on a bodily level, like if somebody puts certain substances in your body or something,
[SPEAKER_00]: Things can happen to you, to your mental state.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eh... underlying tendency has been actually removed when, no matter what happens to that internal environment, in the same way as the external environment doesn't disturb you, well, that wouldn't disturb you either, because you fully understood that the five aggregates are not yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, the qualification to make as well is, eh... any of the actions that happen on the
[SPEAKER_00]: You see, all the things that, so to say, an arahant is incapable of, those things would be inconceivable, even though the mental state that, for an ordinary person, would have led to them, can still be there in its sort of outlines, as I said.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, just to clear up that people don't think like an arahant would go around doing whatever they want, because...
[SPEAKER_00]: These are actions that, if you do them, you took up the ownership of your mental state, of your citta, automatically.
[SPEAKER_00]: You acted out
[SPEAKER_00]: Externally, you were not pure, if you did those actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: But everything in between, like, you know, when the suttas would say, kind of, sometimes, some arahants wouldn't be recognized in the suttas, like, on account of, oh, because he was associating with bad families or whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't mean that he was doing anything, like, against the precepts or whatnot, but somebody else who was maybe more composed, you know, another monk or something, saw that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then he thought, well, he was in doubt about the fact that he was an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the Buddha actually told him, no, actually he is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I say, what's actually blameworthy is to take up another body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: That you're craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, but it's not, it doesn't mean that, like, he would have been, you know, breaking rules and going around.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because those things are necessarily done out of ownership.